It's not none of this and she really will be from the
There's two books to read just came out the stack and dispute plan on both of which were
Partially put together until 7 or so we did here
So this would be suffice going into the next book
The title yet
How to deal with issues of design in philosophy and artificial intelligence is
Particular take on artificial intelligence not as something that
Exist in a kind of abstracted form of symbolic logic
Realm of pure Minds mathematics
But rather something that exists only in the sense it which is embodied instantiated materialized
Particular kinds of ways and how it is it those that instantiation
Is Koh constituted but whatever form of intelligence we might identify
Did Mike I work there
Some of the things that we will be working through I have listed here but no no
Total promises
Go
Contextualize even some of the other things we've been talking about
And thinking of a guy perhaps in relationship to the previous book on the stack
You certainly have to be understood as a certain
Conversion of what we called planetary scale computation the way it works at different scales
Energy and mineral Source in Grid Subterranean Cloud infrastructure Urban software and service privatization
Interfaces drawing my documentation of the hand I directly dissolved into objects users goes over
Outline
Myself quantification or and also exploded into the arrival of Legions of sensors algorithms in
Certain extent that it existed
This level of the user
Within the stock model but not only that really at these other five layers
So pitiful and design or should I say we might have to start with the city as a pen
Mediary I serve it to medium
Level scale by which was supposed to work with your work up and backwards in this as well
It's a first-person pulmonary definition so weird
Looks impossible
Misunderstandings are the way right away
Crystal was talking to cities in this way if something is it kind of is First Source of provisional settlement organized around
Some form of agriculture
Provision
And it says initial
Culinary geoengineering
In which ways in which we reside into as a node on a horizon
Oriental people
And things as they migration flow that is weird looking at the city first visited many capsulating megastructures would hold things in
Play some second is Impreza
Is a throughput point that would accelerate or decelerate things
As they move through them
Lester the particular
Orientation of the city's wayfinding interfaces
Intercity to find in this way with Prospectors mixed wrong mixing from I don't know
Public health planning
Supply chain Logistics
So far in infrastructure for living and non-living matter to consume itself
And for some forms of matter
Some vulgar to achieve and Hound something like Cynthia
Intelligence and even Sapient intelligence and some syrup
All of which in turn and in various ways
Where to remake the city
In their own image
It might take about the server account and going to buy things one of the things we've been working on his deep address projects going for what I'm looking at the
Theoretical address will say some IPv6 which is next Generation internet addressing system
What's 128 bit string
DC Universe we never run out of ipv4 addresses this
Internet on now which is a theoretical 16-bit string
Impossible addresses
128 strings for the back of the
Envelope calculation how to works that works out to something like 10 to the 23
Addresses
Per person
Text request
Level of the granularity by which something like a ubiquitous computing
Might actually operate
Far below and above
The kind of attitude marantika metric sing that dark
Conventional internet-of-things discourse work
So we're interested in this question about how it is it synthetic and augmented intelligence by operator the urban scale
At that level of granularity in all the way on not just the things that appear to us in the scaling which were used to
Addressing a man being a good wife
Also will say just the purposes of this conjunction of some discussions what we mean exactly by artificial intelligence
Persuade some
Misinterpretations we would we Define or would propose a version of intelligence in this way to find this as a
Is the president the way that matter organizes itself into some form of durable complexity
The special form of that complexity being the city
I got settled accumulation of betrayal intelligence both human and
Until
As AI becomes more sophisticated what does it its own design project
What should it be
Till we see in the one-handed episode of weight of a new anime matter to the skill and also me to dissolve
Constructed into
Intimate Turnberry scales in various ways
The same thing
If we make some distinctions then between robotics on the one hand programmable matter on the other hand
Culinary materialism on the third hand
Tangible media on the fourth hand
So is to bring them together backing
Icai
Not as something something
Might happen
Future
The thing that happens after
Some great Messianic moment but is
Something that we see all around us all the time
Terms of a net in the form of an in terms of a kind of synthetic reason that we are always
We are in the process of Designing and designating
In which pitch
Becomes too in its own way contribute to the formulation of our own designation
Of ourselves
End of it
Intern
We also see it in it what philosophy of Mind was the other mind problem
That we might
Communicate
Identifying be identified by that intelligence
One with which we can only share very at least very partial
World
Just don't we're just not invited in the world in the same way we do
The terms of those communicator
Sensory questions
Sweeping
Lamb salerosa Clark's 2001
Communication
I said we try to Cai not in terms of how we think that we stink
Image of ourselves
Virtual or artificial human cognition
Only
But as something that has a way in which matter thinks and embodies another spot in a larger
Shared continuum
Of material intelligence up which our own accomplishments of sapience alright
Particularly
Are one particular form genre
Right and social situation these than once more bringing these together into something like a common frame with assertive
Projecting some way across
Stock thesis which proposes
Own way of particular kind of
Design model for
Political geography term to the question of planetary scale
Mutation
Subway sandwiches of starting with the technology working from the inside out to the governance towards the questions of sovereign chain-smoking cell
Where we want to locate
The AI would locate to AI locate us
Any different skills is not all the same
We want to hold them apart in a certain
Note to the design question so quickly begin to sort of at its beginning with some disclaimers were talking about the rise and says no
Network Platforms in a physical world
And services geared towards an it in towards as we wanted differentiate this from certain kind of conventional smart cities discourse it
See the rise of those in terms of Justice
Prosaic forms of consumption in marketing pedestrian flow optimization
I'm not I hope talking about son of hybrid of The Truman Show Alpha bills of the soixante smartcat
Controlling production variations this is not really what interest to me
It's not about the way in which these Technologies my
Amplify or optimize
He's going to dog sit relation to the world with the way in which that they would crack open other
Other
Again to jump I didn't we would ask then after something like intelligent how is it that in this conjunction of computer
Location of an algorithmic mechanism of computation becomes a kind of solvent
Are the particular form of algorithmic Reason in various kinds of matter we take it for example the computation was to
Discovered more than it was invented
And at the algorithmic Jenna two processes that we might find our intrinsic to The Wider unfolding
The world
Today's meteor computational appliances
I'm nowhere near as sophisticated and efficient as those that proceed
Homosapien
We take it the computations one of the ways that matter whatever format to use a television series procedural abstraction that we make tap in
To Wrangle
On some kind of provisional level one way or another
And as such Sapient brain tissue is one kind of matter that has achieved intelligence insert
Both some of which both clearly are and other clearly not
Computational in any
Conventional center
At the largest can we take it that the solute that's solution dissolution of synthetic computation software
In other words into the urban fabric
Provides for a landscape of inorganic forms to sort of distributed intelligence because it
Provide those things with the capacity for themselves
For abstraction
I'll talk a bit about
In a month
We see intelligent in this way as a
Form of something that accomplishes abstraction
Computation that is
Intelligent and computation then it's a kind of
Mechanism of
Attraction how matter abstraction
This principle should account for two
Related but different understandings one would recognize as I say that intelligence and
College for that matter
Is always distributed among multiple positions and forms of life both similar and dissimilar to one another
That no single neuroanatomical disposition as a privilege Monopoly on how to think
Intelligent
What might qualify as general intelligence is not duty-bound to BC's or file
In his capacity for abstract
We might say no ways of thinking of it in terms of the ability of any organism however primitive
To map the surroundings is this function
Particularly in relationship
To the basic terms
A friend food
Workflow
This is a from primordial a distraction from which we do not graduate
So much as we learn to develop
Into something like a more formal
Reason and its local
Human
Variation
Protozoa
Silly and figuring out what's on non going on around at this is basic kind of mapping is this
I think the primordial formula
Mapping function of attraction
Is not been through an early stage through which things pass on their way to more complex forms of intelligence gets rather Jen
General principle of that complexification
As I say it like the protozoan the Cilia feeling about the weather out there
Or like humans looking and tasting and imagining patterns
Today's high or sometimes augmented by various Technologies machine cognition sensation in Vision that allowed them
I want to see incense the world out there
I do abstract forms of mechanically embodied intelligence both deliberately program for them and
Emerging unexpectedly
DeSoto
Emergent particular
Form of a certain kind of distribution of the sensible if you like
Shipping certain kinds of
Pinterest humor
Jakarta merleau-ponty if you like back again I want to go to think of these really up to the rest of the talk to if I discuss with you some of these
First
A kind of thinking
First will discuss with her challenge of conventional touring test models humanistic models of thought that would that would
Measure them for their epistemological and practical dangers
From the deep into structure of their effects looked to be today gather under the name of a on will shift done or what
Counselors thinking but what counts is Arkansas
Your name is Will
Will try to evade the presumption that when will identify and recognize the threshold of an artificial intelligence to the
Said that it's recognizable similar to our own
Second Skin
Epidermal media synthetic skin in the design convergence of natural sensation and machine sensing
For animal skins like around but also put Riven skins and surface is an interface isn't implications of this for what
We may have one called rolling
And lastly Machine Vision
Camouflage
The inverse uncanny valley
Artificially intelligent paranoia
And I'm a female
First
Thinking
Carini's you know
Trinis you know proposed his test as a variation on the popular parlor game the imitation game in which two hidden contest
He woman
Play hooray
And a man player be hard to convince a third player that he or she is a woman
By the written responses to Leading question
To win one of the players must
Convincingly be who they really are whereas the other must try to pass
As another gender
Entering sasak 9050 would you rather than centimeters or whatever computer took the place of player a
Is really suggesting it was just a waste of computer take a picture of a person to try to suggest they are vacuuming but they would try to pretend to be
Woman
Literal reading with the mathematician Turing his health also has a pass
In his case is a straight man in society to criminalize homosexuality and upon the discovery that he was not what he appeared to be
He was forced to undergo horrific medical experiments
Treatments
Known as chemical castration
How to make the physical and emotional pain is too great and he committed suicide
The episode being
Grotesque tribute to a man whose recent contribution to defeating Hitler's military was still estate Secret
Turing suicide was only recently given up
Posthumous pardon but tens of thousands of other
British man sentence under similar laws
Up to date have not
One notes I think I kind of sour ironic correspondence between asking an AI to pass that
Testing order qualifies intelligent
Cast of the human intelligence
Return Zone need to hide his own
I have a sexuality to pass is a straight man
The demands of both blocks are unnecessary and profoundly unfair and it's for all passing
The performance is success
Orfalea reveals more about the audience
In about the
In other in other places of some infections policing the imitation game is a matter of life and death
Photos of Ridley Scott's film version of Do Androids Dream of Electric Sheep Blade Runner
It's okay good novel hinges on the voight-kampff empathy test
What you differentiate
Humans from Africa
In this narrative replicants are throttled in two important ways first base fire at the Disco
A few years and two they have ostensibly a rather diminished capacity
For empathy
Decker the Harrison Ford character must retire a group of rogue replicants
But first you must find them and in this world
Turing test thresholds
Are weaponized
Left replicant pass as humans and trespass the on their station
By the Stones conclusion Deckard poo himself may or may not be a replicant
Develops
A certain empathy we might say for the replicants own desire for quote
More life
And arguably they to at least Roy Batty Rutger Hauer
Characters seem to have empathy for deckard's own dilemma
His dilemma and hours
Is that in order to enforce the gap between the human and the II defined by empathy or lack thereof
Deckard must suppress the empathy that supposedly makes him
Uniquely
Human
I forcing him to quash his own identification with the replicants that supposedly cannot have empathy and Rich
Turn the principle of differentiation requires its own violation
In order to maintain itself
Far better icing to examine in terms of thinking about how this
Salmon identification and the identification of production of the aspect of empathy
Works from our side of the conversation
Paro the baby robot seal
It's clearly much easier to make a robot
Did human believes to have emotion
And for which human intern may have emotion
Positive or negative entities to make a robot that actually has those ammo
The human may feel love or hate or comfort from the area but if he or she is reading choose not
Detecting feelings
What seems like empathy is really a one-way projection mistaken for recognition
Like the Turing test itself
And not based on any Mutual solidarity
Wheels the wish to define the very existence of a i in relationship
To its ability to mimic
How humans think that humans think
Will this be look back on as some weird form of species
Perhaps may also get the Legacy this also that does this Legacy the older models of AR Easter Sunday sent this
This research down
Disappointingly fruitless pass hoping to recreate human Minds from top down at the basic structure and it's just
Doesn't work
Stuart Russell and Peter norvig remind us in the essential AI textbook
Biomorphic imitation
Is not
How we design complex technology
Airplanes don't fly like birds
And we surely don't try to convince
Try to trick Birds into thinking the airplanes are birds in order to test whether these planes really are flying machine
So why do we do this for AI
Today the vast majority of
Serious core AI research is not focus on the Turing test is anything like essential cratering if he says other than
Hair human artificial hugs interaction research
As a question was General popular discourse about the tests
Versions of it's been sent the anthropocentrism thereof hold such
Still such conceptual important
Like the animals to talk like teenagers in a Disney movie other minds are conceivable mostly by way
Apura ventriloquism
Should a I arrived it will not be human-like unless we insist that it pretend to be so
Because one assumes the idea that intelligence could be both real
And inhuman at the same time as somehow morally or psychologically intolerable
Instead of nurturing is bigotry we would do better to allow that in our universe
Thinking
Is a much more diverse even alien
Phenomenon that our own pictures with case
That's the real philosophical issues and lessen the delay I will have less to do with humans teaching machine how to
Teaching humans
Fuller into a range of what thinking
Is
Can be
Now
In addition to the
Demystification expansion of thinking in this way in the relocation of human sapiens within this expanded form
The sensory media of synthetic intelligence may also contribute to a certain kind of undermining of
Certain forms of adorable
Conti and sort of the philosophical distinction between thinking and sense
I want a home in a bit on the ways in which that kind of cartographic abstraction nothing without their
Can infect also be dermal
Related to skin
It occupies an agitate skins human skins building skins any skin
And how this does so also for the purposes of methane
Until I touch briefly on
Extending what
Skin based media epic start an epidermal media can be
Humans from we recognize that well
In the late nineteenth Century Cinema and photography allowed
Ford Apostle to compose and to see
Sort of images we had never seen before
Montage slow motion double exposure
Synthetic and recorded sound for auditory senses
Our largest sensory organ
However quite obviously today not develop nearly as diverse forms of sophisticated
For the article cut short tactility were feeling on foreskin base Medias we have for vision
And hearing
Clothing are you least one way that we have leap frog genetic Evolution to augment skin
Faster faster than evolving for blubber into engineer school buses
So part of the research that working will try to research engagement UC San Diego
Geopolitics in collaboration with our department Emanuel engineering bioengineering is this is some exploratory research and
How old is
Let's say they presume
Space of difference between natural selection on the one hand
A machine sensing on the other
Is a lighted by certain technologies that operate in and on the skin and at the scale of are dermal and F
Ectodermal somatosensory system
Mechanoreceptors thermoreceptors and so forth and some kind of
Triple o word game by which nucleus machines are bequeath with panpsychic capacities for oven
Tuition has sex rather I referred you Real Deal Technologies by which biological and non-biological physicochemical
Are literally interwoven can edit the scale on sensitive skin
Artificial Skins are also among one of the four areas groups of
Design research more generally in this regard before examples long funded Research into
Advanced Prosthetics
Concurrently wanted to research tracks
Focuses on providing
Synthetic tactile sensation on Virtual fingertips that might go in the end of those pathetic
Look like she wearing them Steel
Using the way to feel it
And other kinds of dermal surfaces of for the kwikpen able alcapurria extensions for the wear
In other words I say another lapse wasn't near us when can find varieties of epidermal micro electronics at all
Augment the living skins capacities for sensing internal extra
Internal or external
Next Roadies
Nanoscale chemistry Cooks of inks
That react to the presence of ambient Trace elements of whatever particles their tune to react with
Kentucky signing
Chemical sensitivity at or near the atomic level in this case and the registration of those as a transmissible infer
Formation with dermal and epidermal microelectronics at largest scales
We can conceive really of a grilled mediatisation of Sensei
Surfaces
Together these Technologies suggest something like a skin base microstack
Price of biological and chemical and mechanical sensing and processing in various combinations
As an emerging formulation of wearable Computing here also including biochemical reactions
Did I say animal sensation machine sensing into a kind of composite surficial media
This platform for haptic interfaces at auction motion division it's terms of
Interaction
Maybe below or above normal perceptual scales
It may involve autonomic nervous reactions as much as if not more than the relatively blood gestures
Hands and stones
Trace and delete these dermal-epidermal media both ones we have the ones we're in the ones that we
Anticipate
Make it possible to sense things about the external World other that our skin otherwise is not able to register
Particulate matter sensor the skills part 4
PH balance in your sweat
But the longer-term and really more interesting
Design Horizon for skin basement
I want to do it allow bodies
Novel and unnatural form to touch sensation
We have perhaps never experienced
Pleasure in pain or on the menu but more
Early in experimental media and Renovations with with artificial Visions insights and South
Also perhaps is Molecular Gastronomy in the rebuilding of food from first principles on up
And if we include taste
Is it particularly Nuance going to touch
Which of course it is
Then
Weather today novel tastes are models for New Sensation
The same holds true I was hoping to argue for the redesign of the surfaces of the city
Its skin
Urban interfaces are also sensory mechanisms sometimes their binary gateways that allow or prohibit admission
Other times there are reactive skins that sense threshold events
My reaction to light sound and touch
Debian Trace elements
And as we Meander the city these interfaces are also our habitat
We dwell within them
But they are dwelling as well
They sent us as their world and we are their habitats as much as they are ours
We are organisms living inside of them just as they are inside of us
Ubiquitous Computing Adam in the City skins and surfaces of interfaces
We see is something like urbanism as
Necessary ism
What nasty parasitism
From touching
To see it
But shipping is line of inquiry up to the servants kill this way what we take to be the artificially mediated
Surface includes things that are
Analogous to skin
But we sure but we would also those things we would today refer to colloquially
As a kind of machine
Vision protocol
Vision has evolved independently many times
Evolutionary history and arguably in the past two decades or so it has a vault again
This time not for cuttlefish or rattlesnakes but for Network CCD sensors and algorithmic armatures
Processing what is sensed into differentiating
Differentiating and motivated
Cut recognition in cognition
Quote unquote visual sensors responding to light
Often but not always shaped like Cameron
Are one kind of design surface
Capable of synthetic sensation
And computational interpretation
Put in the wider Urban landscape they to commingle with networks of other surficial sensors responding to
Motion and pressure and heat and ambient air quality so poor
Until I get to the extended epistemological and something convenient we call these very soon Machine Vision
Missing hearing machine skin but of course any real correspondence
To and from the mammalian sensory apparatus
Amelia allegory
The AI City maybe inviting itself but it's also a few times not as weak
Aspen media technology that links it to
But we pieced together answer tonight until particular question envision
Ford light
You might say that when information is scarce
Then copying something
Is the work of the mechanical image
However
When information is abundant
Especially when it's over London
Then seeing the original
Picking a pattern out of the background
This is the work of Machine Vision
Quick-thinking animals seeing and making things is easy but making copies of what it's insane and made it hard
But machines on the other hand making copies
Is a way of seeing
Is much easier than thinking
Warcraft is a kind of thinking
And in the very history of the multiple and as I say independent evolutionary careers division
Various photoreceptor cells found across
Viola may have evolved many different kinds of chemoreceptors
Most likely well in advance of anything we might recognize each other
Polyflex brain like information processing order
Further we could say that
Photosynthesis is also
In the chemical response to light
And so in the broadest sense it to could be considered as it kind of
Vision Without images
Within the atom allien Vision image making Nexus
The one that we
Primarily human
Likely that's from the beginning to the end of the hall of fame
The total quantity of images that humans are produced
Cave walls to FaceTime
Measures
Per year
Total pounds of images total terabytes in information so far
Continues to increase
Exponentially
Now with digital imaging machines and everyone's pocket
The rawsome of total images produced
Some days until your 2005-2008
Maybe more than all of those produced
Up to that moment
Depends of course in how you define quantify an image
But
But both of them even called mechanical reproducing reproducibility is certainly allowed
Images to proliferate far beyond the means
If You Can Craft
Further today many images are made for No One
But this does not mean that their function was
They're made by in for machines that see the world differently than we do
Those machines don't have eyeballs are rods and cones or visual cortex but they do have sensors
The detect light and motion inform and heat and color
In other ways
And Saturdays at the industrial scale processing of that data that has been cleaned by scanning the light spectrum in Sun
Urban scale
Treat your family can millimeter scale quality control along assembly lines
Represents a significant fraction of all of the work that the world does the image itself for the purpose
Laws governing Human Society
The end of the day
Let me see me find them
I take more selfies than cells do
However the function of representation
At work here is probably rather differ
The quote on quote image
May likely remain
Data
Is never rear-ender to look like a picture
Because there's no need
An algorithm program to discern a particular pattern or normally can see it directly in the date itself
It doesn't necessarily need for that day to be projected
Is it for a mammal and then reason and reinterpreted back into
Code like any
Like like any algorithmic scanning and sorting of a
Any large dataset the fact
That the original source
Was or is
Visual
Is not so critical
So again like plants do machines also possess a kind of
Vision Without images
Or at least an image kind of damage with that suggested very different form of abstraction Twitter very different
Kind of Corporal experience
An abstraction the space on chemical or informational pattern finding as as that cartographic simulation of it
Or as that experience itself
Perhaps
Surprising to some apps not to others
Identity
Function of machinic images today and other abstractions
Both animal and algorithm
Is it many cases if not actually predominantly to determine
The veracity and originality
What does images supposedly represent
For example
Some of the shades printed on dollar bills or bureaus
Are there for humans to differentiate the value of one token from another
Far more are Ford Machine Vision counterfeit detection to verify that this is a real dollar
Piece of paper is full of machines that happened to look like pictures
It is an image as machine
Or a surveillance cannabis City make pick out one face one body from thousands of motions looking for the one
True Target
Elsewhere we insert tiny Camera Pro into great paintings for to verify that they are Originals
This is often required by Insurance Company
Stacking purchases
Online capture software shows us an image and then in a quick
Conversion of the Turing test analyzes how the human user interpreted to determine if they are in fact
A real person
So we can clue perhaps that venue means assurances that mechanical reproduction would undermine the aura
The original
Is true when for example we compare a painting with a postcard of a painting
However Machine Vision and images as machines
Put to work to ensure
O'rielly Collision
They're fighting on fakes
True identity unbroken version
Normal Target certified Real Deals
Until kind of revolution is made back around as the image is more fully teknologize
As it becomes itself a machine and some k
Then benyamin's historical Ark from the pre-mechanical original to Mechanical copy is incomplete without another curve
Leaving now
To what
Machine Aquatics
Still
If we if we if cities are always in there some way about vision
Sunday great again
Disappeared
As well
We think of this in terms of how we see it
Which is fine
Or see each other through it
Supply
But you also think of it in terms of how it sees on its own car
The machine visual subject
What sport is not something that's that possesses necessarily human-like or human-level perceptual anesthetic
Capacities
Discernment of connoisseurship
But rather something that is interesting because it does not possess those things
And yet can see us
Recognizes
And Noah's regardless
And that's
Weird enough
So there's the question of the white-haired how the world looks as a screen and another
More important I think it's how we look as objects of perception from the position of machines with weave
Which we
Kolacky pie
That world
Seeing ourselves Through The Eyes of this machine and other who does not
Cannot have an active sense of Aesthetics is it kind of
Disenchantment
We are just stuff
In the world for distributed metric machine cognition to look at and to make sense of our own sapience is real
And unique
But as we are things to observe that just happened to the Sapient
This doesn't really matter
Two machines
Distance from Shamrock I think it's more than just like hearing the sound of the record this recorded sound of your voice
Possibly be me
It's potentially the clearing away of a more closely guarded
Illusion
Uncomfortable recognition in the machines mirror the kind of perhaps reverse uncanny valley
Instead of being creeped out that has slightly in human the creature in the image appears were creeped out at Hell on human weave
We ourselves look
Through the creatures eyes
Politics of this are also a bit
Writing a book about artificial intelligence
I found some ways I can expect it
In many ways fully impossible to separate
The technology itself from the sometimes bizarre ideas that we have for it and about it
Reason fascinated by how Technologies are not only anthropomorphised
Because Summer considered menacing and others amazing and some both at once
The way in which part of the system part of the genealogy that we might take me out at least through
The Towson the influencing machine
About the ways in which this
This apparatus just the younger understanding
Take on a condom
Psychiatric significance
Whether the aliens are reading your thoughts through radio waves in dental implants or Google is reading your thoughts to the email
The Borderlands between schizophrenia and sensible vigilance
Delusion and deductions are
Disputed territory
Perhaps it comes down to a level of discomfort not just with how some people see technology but we have some people think Tech
Nology see them
The occult artifacts of planetary scale computation are a cracked mirror and reflection
Scene there are given to
Medicann and dualistic and sometimes even bipolar
Political psychiatric
Imaginary
For example deepdream
Last summer was here we had to study dreams this get these are they self tell you about these are the moments images of research and release
Sometimes this summer
Before Franco Berardi and I were having breakfast as well he and I should be done for
We don't usually think about Google in the same ways let's say
But we were both totally amazed
Ongoing conversations about this really read these represent
A new kind of image we haven't seen before it's so he's such a long time
Basically
Every newspaper
What's the project undertaken by Google research where you insensitive
Object recognition algorithm to analyze large data sets and look for particular things
Photo app Note
Which which face you are that's a horse or dog dressed up as well they're interested in the weather like
How did what kind of feedback loops could this order provide what happens if it tries to see something that's not there but you force it to
See it again or use you asking to see it so often says well this is kind of what this done
In the simplest of explanation that the process is kind of simple find edges function like you might learn Photoshop where you should have filled
2D image to should make the edges everything fit more what it is in relationship to things around it
You didn't ask me to look for the thing but it's looking for
And then you do this again
And then you could do it again and then again and you feed this back through the system over and over and over and over and over again and it starts to actually
Depressing
Find things that is looking for that aren't actually there
Kind of
AI
Hallucination
If you like
Now there's a bunch of websites you can go to even take your own vacation photos and upload them and have them deep dream of find
Food is horrible to do this as well
P**** solo
Not recommended
The images I think a remarkable enough on their own irrespective of their
Providence but once the viewer I think makes the
Partial and crystals partial empathetic transference into the other mind of the speaker recognition algorithm in
It's way of seeing some
The effects of trying on a new motor perception
Making sense of the world through those eyes
That's the real payoff
Even if it's an example is it to hear what kind of AI
Phenia
False positive
As a quart
What is the following
Stop on this remember what is a poppy apophenia is the psychological phenomenon of false pattern recognition
But you see a pattern in something that's not really there
Parody Lia is the subtype of five apathy when you see faces in things that aren't really there and receiving weather Yuma
Whether you want to or not you can say I'd Sonata face I know it's not a phase you're going to see a face it's not necessarily A
Kind of
Process that you can be
Disenchanted of by just by
Beat Hotel
What is the schizophrenia causation causality Dynamic where you see some correspondence between things I need to do sit there must be some
I'm called the relationship between deceiving in general instructions
About Buffet
Conspiracy theories apophenia as a form of political science
What is who we are and what we do is that this kind of pattern finding even the false pattern finding is intrinsic
And necessary
QR
Evolution that you are taken
We R Who We R Who can't set up junk junk without it
Think of it this way there's a character
Penfield really good novels about AI
Tropical echopraxia
And in this story one of the character relays this this this
Affinia to one of the other characters
Is the character that argues that this false pattern recognition is hardwired
Into
Are Homo sapiens evolution
Except some story goes like this ten thousands of years ago two guys are hiding in the tall grass
Quietly looking around for both predator and prey
One of them see the faint but distinct anomaly in the White Delight brakes to the grass moving left to right and you recognize it
This is pattern of that of a looming
He runs away back to the Village
Leaving his friend
Who does not possess the pattern recognition Gene
To be eaten
The guy who ran away was able to reproduce his pattern-recognition jeans and sure his and their survival
And the guy who did not possess those jeans did Don reproduce
However
It was a third guy
Sitting in a similar graph perhaps the morning earlier
He too thought there was a tiger and got up and ran back to the safety of the village
But in this case
There was no tiger
It was all in his mind
He was not cutting
He was paranoid
Yep he too was able to respond reproduce and his faulty pattern recognition jeans which or perhaps actually the same thing
Actor pattern recognition genes were also able to reproduce
As well perhaps with the second guys
The lesson is that Evolution has greatly rewarded both positive
Successful human pattern recognition
It's also found inexplicably
The Bounty of that bargain
It is also rewarded hallucination
And error
And so
It's one thing
Caution
Paranoia
About Google
But it's but it's not as if Google's algorithms are
RR
Art themselves as if they are not themselves also deeply paranoid
After all they see psychedelic log faces in everything
The reason the teaching hallucinating dogs is itself not spooky its object recognition faculties
Are you trained doing an image dataset called imagenet
Which is based on various breeds of dogs
You can try. I'll look different you train the recognition identify the poodle and a great day and I love her all constitute dog is this
And so it won't therefore hallucinate dogs
Where there are none and to identify people as dogs if it's told to look at them hard enough
The spider may seem insulting but maybe it shouldn't you to call the diogenes
Proto cosmopolitanism is based after all in the Glorious dog like
Until deep dreams images are artifacts of computers hallucinations of phantom conclusions then
Perhaps the conspiratorial figure cut by
Eagle Google evil Google stepfather
Is that same paranoid Vision turn inside out and back on
Perhaps Google the eye is it paranoid and how it sees us as some of us are and how we see it
It's not coincidental or surprising than yours
Its own pattern recognition faculties would reach the plateau and accomplishments of creative apophenia
Go to Seymour cray
Ways in which we have perceived some kind of homology between abnormal human psychology in various machine
Haters
Intro
Is Machine Vision paranoid
Is our popular understanding of Machine Vision
What is Google up to
You are they watching you and if so who or what
I received
Is our understanding of Google's paranoid Machine Vision itself paranoid making me paranoid AI that much more
Paranoid
In a word yes
Is this how artificial intelligence should evolve in relation to ship to and autonomously from humans
Elliot's
Where is the pattern recognition and pattern recognition human pattern recognition is any indicator
Bass both unproductive
And destructive apophenia deception and delusion
Then yes or no
Moving then back up
N scale to the
To aru machine sensing as a whole
At the level of the whole city
I'm in this redistribution of the responsible
Again
Dai City maybe embodying itself but not as
We do
Commingling a diver sensor satellite and Aaron sound chemistry girls up
A landscape of sensing and thinking little species
Partially embodied discreetly
One with another and partially covering body with one another
As their information inputs are aggregated modeled
After the pain
In various plurality
Homo sapiens comes equipped with an extraordinary array of sensory faculties which is we
Discuss maybe augmented further by synthetic layers
In various ratios ranging from the sensors and trackers in our phones that we carry about like meals
Two more intimate media of surface of artificial images in Sight and Sound
Situating ourselves in this expanded field
Again we are both sensors and sense
On the one hand we are primary Sapien actor in the drama supervising Orchestra of sense
Technology capable of functional processing in together of certain forms of aggregate emergency College
As stars
On the other we're not only the subject of the scenario we are also its subject matter
The Wider Urban Landscaping synthetic Century systems is not only a platform through which we extend and extract
Appellate are capacities for abstraction distributed cognition it's also capable of other sorts of Attraction on its own
Is part of its intelligence it looks at us and registers abstraction
About
Mackenzie in the city
But nested AI Cohen bodied as the city
With very different sorts of organisms to population to Gino Tanish to signal morphologies
At work
And that's the
Work of abstraction
Forward
What design more generally is not only to deploy abstract forms but to set in motion mechanisms
And programs that are capable of their own feet
Other traction
How to calibrate how they abstract us in one another
According
In short we should imagine an AI organism of different room instead of like vondelstraat stroll
The field populated by intermingling but neutrally oblivious little life worth
Origins of the losses parable of the tick
The later wait laying in wait for some threshold event to come its way which point
It's triggers
Programmed response sleeping out
Into its own
Little void
Many of our Urban sensors and their limited forms of AI
Work similarly
And was similar nobility
More versatile synthetic intelligence occupy more complex on felt some more predators and prey summary
Rocking motion summer flowering some pollinating
And if we stroll along then we may be registered by them or we may be ignored
Maybe a primary cause of concern we may be a passing interference in an evolutionary dynamic in which we are neither
The protagonist
Your target
And this is anyway as we might expect
Actually not surprised
Kino
Ships from top-down to bottom-up AI
Mark by shift of emphasis from
Intelligence is a formal syntax
To one of a specifically embodied relation to specific world
And models
Heuristic knowledge of habitat is seen as Inseparable from how an AI manipulates
Is situated problem
Until we bought it with a pairing of synthetic
Example allows for
Simple artificial species to perform intelligently because they have what amounts do functionally
Anybody
Perceptual relocation the world they can sink because they can see
D
The implications of all of this
Politics geopolitics in the rest of this as I say rotten
Tangled
Banal and various measures
Extension the biochemistry of climates and ecosystems to the rhetorical conventions of citizenship and sovereignty it's messy
Cai so we're talking about not a kind of clean and pure AI
Interlocking food presentation with a few
Admonitions
For the general
Disciplinary design
Brake for AI and for what we
My calls
Post anthropocene
It is
At best
A paradoxical accomplishment to survive a mass extinction event
The modern human species has the dubious distinction of gnarly observing and measuring mass extinction while it is happening but also
Doing so with the understanding that it is one pre of the trim and agents of that
It does so with the
Did ambivalent comfort that get that one way or another it to
Is unlikely to survive
The bloody edge of the anthropocene
So much to parks
Water rhymes
Simultaneously with the collapse of biodiversity
We also see
At least the trunk potential for an explosion of new quotient of species taking form through
Robotics and synthetic biology in artificial intelligence
You can't see the ladder as replacement for the former and yet
There they are
Because for example that the first or things in space
We're not humans
And the very low percentage of all or things in space have been humans
Human biology is needy
Fragile
Is poorly suited to space travel largely because we have to bring an entire ecosystem with us
Oxygen to radiation filters to the microbial biome
In our testing to help us digest food
Currently configured
Human
We cannot really believe Earth because we have to bring a miniature Earth with us
When we go
This is not true in the same way for other species which supervised comparatively easy in space such as metalloid robotics
Jackson perhaps also someday
Some kinds of synthetic biology
And so perhaps like the small mammals that took that fit that took over after the Cretaceous paleocene Extinction
They're just better suited to the very different punctuated equilibrium to come
They may enjoy successes that we cannot
Leaving us behind
Been stranded
Place
So what
Comes then after an anthropocene Extinction
The only thing we can know about the post and prophesying is it it's a Nira in which humans would no longer be that
Dominant geologic actor
Perhaps in New Orleans species may prove to be more fit better at making the next evolutionary step than humans are until 4
R Us to quote survive we may have to become more like them and less like what we are now
The longer view humans roll maybe that of an enabling intermediary
Between early primates
And as yet to emerge phyla that blend organic and inorganic flesh
NSYNC
This is the point of convergence between robust Ai and the Deep ecology of
Voluntary human
Extinction
But
Instead of Disappearing however
We may Survive by Perforating the boundaries between animal vegetable and mineral
Aztec design
Just as art design problem and design solution
What's the oldest age is the death of the users is a certain kind of death of a certain for humanism as any clips of ascertain
Resolute human
It does so because it brings with it also the multiplication and proliferation of other forms of non-human in human
EXO human
Agents in subjects including
Robots nanometric to Landscapes kill any combination of which with which
We may enter into a kind of relationship as a
Deposit
Subject
The complexities and contradictions of those Salvage in relationship to those Composites or nevertheless
With those causing intelligence NSAIDs after
Is this a work to dismember certain conventional distinctions between subject and school occupant and City
And so and so
Introduces a certain kind of a redistribution of a certain kind of
Agnostic universal suffrage
By which it what kind of matter can enter into that position and take on that
Cleaning a strongly
A different kind of strong
Mercurial
Perspective
Encourage more input we anticipate
Without a doubt
But as this
Asterisk works itself out
As a disenchantment unfolds that it there would we went dissipate all manner of pushback
Against this demystified in Demonite
Natalie distaste for certain forms of quantification and preference for romantic verse for example
Put a bull work on behalf of what amounts to a pre copernican and deeply reactionary humanist exception
Even a human is fundamental
I push back as they say it's broken and perhaps is raschke rational that is certain affinity
Certain Technologies however fictitious or bizarre that's Kennedy's maybe they're thought to embody the essence of a kind of cry
Directions to order one of these days
Food
Extend its influence of technology to Personal Mastery sex
Car
Google X was beginning to work on the driver there driverless car project I want to come visit at the labs if there was a student
And mine who is not working on that
Meeting with him is until you guys must have heard a lot of different kind of strange
Strange ideas about what the driverless car system
Going to
Amount to in about what is a pushback from
Well
It's funny you should ask if they pull up this piece of paper with
Attention to file
Potential file preemptive legal notices something which is far as I can tell this
Completely made up
Document
From the group called gunownersofamerica
Which is an advocacy group a bit to the right of the net of the NRA
And if you remember that in United States alone roughly about 30,000 people a year are killed in car accidents butts
28000 the year of those are directly attributable to human driver error and so with driverless cars could kill
27000 people a year or less
They would still PA
From Shirley consequentialist view of ethical
For purposes of President putting a human behind the wheel is just
Too great of a risk
Unethical to put everyone else's
That makes sense
What does legal thing was with this document things that you should
It become illegal for humans to drive a car
In this way that they will see to have automobiles reclassified as ammunition
And thereby covered by the 2nd Amendment to the Constitution which guarantees the right to bear arms in this case
A car
Or
But this way you would like maybe ended by someone in case in a 2-ton steel box careening down the asphalt trying to
To prove a point about his how technology will never capture his natural Humana
All of this is not without real risk we anticipate that this distribution of
Apperception and Co embodiment implied by Senpai I at the urban scale wood
If we are tempted in persistent shift and expand what we take to be an ethics of shelter and Encounter of negotiate
Haitian and even
Immunity
And in this D
Modern era form of proven anime
May pale in comparison to the challenges of predator-prey camouflage dissimulation relationships implied by
Emergence of various
Alien lines in urban scale
Negotiating our way to a livable posting prophecy necessitates
However I still argue a Fidelity to emergency
Not to emergency
Because copernican traumas
Abolish the false centrality and specialness of human thought and species being
Are priceless
Accomplishment
The Advent of robust in human AI
Could provide for similar disenchantments one that should enable a more reality-based understanding of ourselves
Algebra situation and Fuller
And more complex and nuanced understanding of what intelligence is what's thinking is and is not
From there
We can hopefully make our world with greater confidence
There are models are good approximation
Out there
Always
An additional harm and did not unusual harm of the alternative to that
Is in perpetuating a relationship to technology that has brought us to the precipice of a six
Great Extinction
Arguably
50 and throughout the scene itself is due less to technology run amok then to the human is Legacy that
Who stands the world is having been given for our needs and created in our image
We still see this everywhere
Are Computing culture very deeply confused and so and it is so along the same line
Vacillate between thinking technology at the transparent extension of our desires on the one hand and I'm thinking of it as a nun stop
Stop a boil in your historical force on the other
For the first agencies magically ours alone and for the second agencies all in the code
That's gross inflation of the former is really inverted
Back into the other
And this is why we can't have nice
Well known get sloppy in the world of design recently wrote killing remain nameless
It's time to invert invent world war machines are subservient to the needs and wishes of humanity
Simply dressed
If you think so
I invite you to Google
Pig decapitating machine
And then let's talk about inventing world see which machines are holy subservience
The human race
One wonders whether it's only from a society that one skate theological and legislative Comfort to chattel slavery
This particular client could be offered
What's up
Satisfied naivete
This is the sentiment this philosophy of Technology exactly that is the basic algorithm Panther the scenic route
Time to move on
This pretentious folklore
Is too expensive
And so
Differently please to make technology serve humans and serve human needs and desires requirements appear
Utterly misguided and even suicidal
Staring upon the events of mass extinction
We hear the drearily common refrain
Variously explicit or latent
That identifies called modern technology as the main culprit in conclusion that the most fundamental solution
If UD technology is a planet
Into rehumanize yourself
One presupposes the other in various measures
This is among the worst
Possible
Plans
Philosophically
And practice
First Stitch tragically def
To the Priceless copernican trauma of the anthropogenic precipice
Then our status as a dominant geologic actor is fleeting
So in order to survive we would have to become somebody that it's not necessarily recognizably human
And second process of a psychotic misrepresentation with humans
And humanism
Actually are
We are the brain eating eggs with weaponized hydrogen
Organizer societies according to Bronze Age poetry
On human sacrifice and ritual purification
Among the last projects to support
Esri humanization in any sense of a direct return to historical norms
I think the other species would agree
The last reason why do desire
How do we map with a certain technological material to compensate as a theory of subjectivity against the tropes
But with the tropes of Heroes
Tricky
Troy barely had Darwin
To work with let alone genetics and genomics and so she probably repeating some of those terms you're probably a little bit ly
Reese the Greek
Organic versus inorganic
That is whether something is alive or not alive
Kind of the minor is sort of a minor issue
Something having or not having a carbon molecule
Is it the same any any melting back into the inorganic instead of tonic and pull
Interview over comment overwhelmed by
In absorbed by matter itself may be a way of encountering and even Desiring death
Perhaps
He's also in many ways a very everyday kind of occurrence
It's not a sad Destiny to The Interlopers Indian matter and other diagram and other diagrams for that disc
Solution of possible but anatomic
An economic
The human body
And this Earthly landscape of matter are only the default settings
The knot
Destiny
Chemistry may drive the most radical forms of the philosophical imaginary to
A culinary materialism
Rubbing the clinamen Raw
Until he remember algorithms For Whining evolution of vision Returns the primordial function of
Scanning the landscape
Food
Pho
I'm going to thinking relationship to that man
Some alternatives
Do this anyway I think make the
Inevitable
Whether we wanted to or not geoengineering project it really actually constitutes the Eco geopolitics released at 1
That is either
Is qualified a priority as a metaphysical atrocity or something that will simply sort itself
Automatically by the Invisible Hand of Moore's Law
The former
Is animated in various sizes by a kind of mystical primitive primitivism that is to me the field logic Express
Russian of the mode of global
Dwelling that sees the world is here for us
Based on the fetishization of Human Experience of Human Experience
Priority over the materiality of the emergent intelligence
Again it is this humanist exceptionalism that is the exact recipe for anthem
Predicament
In this fetishization of the experience of experience as of it as an authentic interiority for one
For The Psychotic proposition is somehow the self is a stable physical entity that can be expanded exponentially by the fairies from
The complications out exploding into some fractal plurality as for the singularity people
Both of these make that geoengineering project much more difficult than what it is make it harder to recognize it for what it is
Some of it is more like
Molecular Gastronomy at landscape scale
I resorted and Reese and been restored ecology designed to taste itself
The new forms of Richmond spiced and imaginatively sauce
Mutual in chest
Last word
Unless I misunderstood to recommend too much of today's computational cultures is model for the AI design them
Sketching out on by misquoting a sentence the McDonald's minimum Aralia substituting the word smart cities for his original
Topic of Escapist Cinema
It is not because they turn their back on washed-out existence that smart cities are so repugnant but because they do not do so enter
Ethically and nuts
Because they are themselves just as washed out because the satisfactions they fake
Coincide with the enemy of denial
Dreams
Have no dreams