so it's not none of this material really
would be from the this two books that we
just came out the stack and dispute plan
both of which were partially put
together in the seminars that we did
here and so this would be stuff that's
going into the next book which doesn't
have a title yet it has to do with
issues of design of philosophy and
artificial intelligence it's a
particular sort of take on artificial
intelligence not as something that
exists in a kind of abstracted form of
symbolic logic that a realm of pure mind
mathematics but rather something that
exists only in this sense of which it's
embodied and instantiated or
materialized in particular kinds of
waves and how it is that those that
instantiation is Co constitutive of
whatever form of intelligence we might
identify that might work there in this
way and so some of the things that we
will be working through I have listed
here but no no total promises for all of
this early go okay so first sort of
contextualize even some of the other
things that we've been talking about and
thinking of AI perhaps in relationship
to this previous book on the stack it
would certainly have to be understood as
a certain instantiation mr. version of
what we call planetary scale computation
in the way it works at different scales
energy and mineral source and grids
subterranean cloud infrastructure urban
software and service privatization the
interface is drawn by the augmentation
of the hand the eye are directly
resolved into objects users both over
outlined by self quantification or and
also exploded into the arrival of
legions of sensors algorithms and BOTS
and so to a certain extent we're talking
that AI that it exists at this level of
the user within the stack model but not
only that really at these other five
layers as well so particularly in design
will sort of say we might sort of start
with the city as a kind of meaty area as
sort of a kind of medium level scale by
which we discover to work you should
have worked up and backwards from this
as well and so first of all some
preliminary definition so we're sort of
some possible misunderstandings out of
the way right away first of all we're
talking with cities in this way of
something this is a kind of first is a
provisional settlement organized around
some form of agricultural and provision
and that's its initial form of culinary
geoengineering in which we in which we
reside in - as a node on a horizon that
would orient mobile people and things as
they migrated in flow that is we're
looking at the city first is a sort of
encapsulating mega structure that would
hold things in place and second ISM
is a throughput point that would
accelerate or decelerate things as they
as they move through them and move
through the particular orientation of
the city's wayfinding interfaces and so
cities defined in this way with
perspectives mix drawn mixing from I
don't know public health planning supply
chain logistics so forth are an
infrastructure for living and nonliving
matter to consume itself and for some
forms of matter some forms in order to
achieve and hone something like sentient
intelligence and even sapient
intelligence in some circumstances we
all of which in turn and in various ways
work to remake the city in their own
image we might think about this simply
return to count and quantify things one
of the things we've been working on as a
deep address projects going for a while
looking at the theoretical addressable
space of ipv6 which is next-generation
internet addressing system works -
128-bit string the you know which we
never run out of ipv4 addresses this
much with the things that we're running
the address on out with the internet on
now which is a theoretical address a
16-bit string which is about three and a
half billion possible addresses we've
all been allocated the RIR so 128-bit
address strings sort of back with the
envelope calculation council work so it
works out to something like 10 to the 23
addresses per person it begs the
question of like insufficient the level
of the granularity by which something
like a ubiquitous computing might
actually operate far below and above the
kind of notes of mere anti-symmetric
thing that our conventional internet of
thing discourse works is so bad so we're
interested in this question of the how
it is that synthetic and augmented
intelligence might operate at the urban
scale at that level of granularity and
all the way on up not just the things
that appear to us in the scale in which
we're used to by dressing them and being
addressed by them also we'll say just
for purposes of this conjunction of of
some discussions of what we mean reject
made by artificial intelligence to
dissuade some misinterpretations we
would we define or would propose a
version of intelligence in this way to
find us as a system as a way that matter
organizes itself into some form of
durable complexity it's a special form
of that complexity being the city that
settled accumulation of material
intelligence both human and non-human
and so as AI becomes more sophisticated
what does it's its own design project
become what should it be until we see on
the one hand AI is a sort of wait
something to an animate matter and it'll
scale and also something that its
dissolved or the structured into into
matter various scales in various ways
none of which necessarily all add up to
the same thing and so we make some
distinctions then between robotics on
the one hand programmable matter on the
other hand culinary materialism on the
third hand tangible media on the fourth
hand so as to bring them together back
in in different sorts of ways in other
words I see AI not as something
something something might happen in the
future some sort of thing that happens
after some great messianic moment but is
something that we see all around us all
the time and in terms of in the form of
and in terms of a kind of synthetic
reason that we are always we are in the
process of designing and designating and
which it becomes to in its own way
contribute to the formulation of our own
designations of ourselves and of it in
turn we also see it in it what
philosophy of mind calls the other mind
problem how it is that we might
communicate and identify and be
identified by that
one with which we can only share very at
least very partial world just don't were
just not embodied in the world in the
same way we don't think the same white
so how those terms of those communicate
on which is sir
same sort of questions we might agree as
we've been talking in seminary my readin
lens Solaris or Clark's 2001 release
into other kinds of alien communication
and so we try to see AI not in terms of
how we think that we think that is as an
image of ourselves in this way as a kind
of virtual or artificial human cognition
only but as something that as a way in
which matter thinks and embodies another
spot in a larger shared continuum of
material intelligence of which our own
accomplishments of sapiens are a
particularly are one particular form
genre example right and so just situate
these than once more bringing these
together into something like a common
frame with you sort of but project them
in some way across the stack thesis
which proposes in its own way a
particular kind of design model for
political geography tuned to the
question at planetary scale computation
the ways in which is starting with the
technology working from the inside out
to the governance towards the questions
of sovereignty and silver and selling so
where we want to locate the AI where
locating a AI locates us in these
different scales is not all the same we
want to hold them apart in a certain
kind of way now to the design question
sort of quickly again to sort of at the
beginning was in disclaimers we're
talking about the rise and sort of
network platforms in a physical world
and services geared towards I mean
towards this we want to differentiate
this from a certain kind of conventional
smart cities discourse that would see
the rise of those in terms of just
prosaic forms of consumption and
marketing pedestrian flow optimization
so forth I'm not I hope talking about a
sort of hybrid of The Truman Show with
alpha v Lovelace Watson to smart control
in production variations this is not
really what
to me it's not about the way in which
these technologies might amplify or
optimize these kinds of toxic relations
to the world but the way in which that
they would crack open other other forms
of kinds of relationships so again to
jump right in we would ask then after
something like intelligence how is it
that the in this conjunction of
computation of the algorithmic
mechanisms and matter itself computation
becomes a kind of solvent of a
particular form of algorithmic reason in
various kinds of matter we take it for
example the computation was discovered
more than it was invented and that the
algorithmic generative processes are
that we might find are intrinsic to the
wider unfolding of the world and for
today's Meteor computational appliances
are nowhere near as sophisticated and
efficient as those that precede Homo
sapiens we take it the computation is
one of the ways that matter in whatever
form achieves at elegance to its
procedural abstraction that we may tap
in to wrangle on some kind of
provisional level one way or another and
as such sapiens brain tissue is one kind
of matter that has achieved intelligence
in certain ways both some of which both
clearly are and others are clearly not
quote computational in any conventional
sense at the larger scale we take it
that the solute that solution
dissolution of synthetic computation
software in other words into the urban
fabric provides for a landscape with
inorganic forms - sort of distributed
intelligence because it provides those
things with the capacity for themselves
for abstraction which I'll talk a bit
about in a moment that is we see
intelligence in this way as a form of
something that accomplishes abstraction
computation then is a form of
intelligent and computation then it's a
kind of mechanism of abstraction how
matter abstraction cells so this
perspective in principle should account
for two two related but different
understandings one would recognize as I
say that intelligence and knowledge for
that matter is always distributed among
multiple positions and the four
of life both similar and dissimilar to
one another that no single
neuroanatomical disposition as a
privileged monopoly on how to think
intelligently what might qualify as
general intelligence is not duty-bound
to species or phylum in its capacities
for abstraction we might say no ways of
thinking of in terms of the ability of
any organism however primitive to map
its own surroundings is this function of
abstraction particularly in relationship
to the basic terms of friend food or foe
this is a kind of primordial abstraction
from which we do not graduate so much as
we learn to develop into something like
a more formal kind of Reason in its
local human variations thinking though
from 9000 protozoan it's silly under
some figuring out what's on going on
around it this is a basic kind of
mapping is that it's the primordial form
of abstraction and in this way the
mapping function of abstraction is not
then through an early stage through
which things pass on their way to more
complex forms of intelligence it's
rather general principle of that
complexification as I say like the
protozoa cilia feeling about so what's
out there or like humans looking and
tasting and imagining patterns
today's AI or sometimes augmented by
various technologies machine cognition
sensation and vision that allowed them
to see and sense the world out there and
to abstract forms of mechanically
embodied intelligence both deliberately
programmed for them and emerging
unexpectedly so this sort of a sort of
emergent particular form of a certain
kind of distribution of the sensible if
you like shifting certain kinds of
interest from a jacquard from
merleau-ponty if you like back again I
want to sort of think of these really in
hopes for the rest of the talks or if I
discuss with you sort of these in terms
of three ways first a kind of thinking
first we'll discuss was no challenge of
conventional Turing test models
humanistic models have thought that
would that would
and measure them for their
epistemological and practical dangers
from the deep interest structure of
their effects what do we today gather
under the name of a I will shift not
only what counts is thinking but what
counts as architecture naming will will
try to evade the presumption that when
will identify and recognize the
threshold of an artificial intelligence
to the extent that it's recognizable is
similar to our own second skin
epidermal media synthetic skin and the
design convergence of natural sensation
and machine sensing for animal skins
like our own but also for urban skins
and surfaces and interfaces and
implications of this for what we may
have once called dwelling in per se and
Lashley machine vision camouflage the
inverse uncanny valley artificially
intelligent paranoia and apophenia first
to thinking no touring is you know mrs.
Alan Turing Turing as you know proposed
his test as a variation on the popular
parlor game the imitation game in which
two hidden contestants a woman player a
and a man player be tried to convince a
third player that he or she is a woman
by their written responses to leading
questions to win one of the players must
convincingly be who they really are
whereas the other must try to pass as
another gender entering seven 1950 which
were in the seminar matrix but what if a
computer took the place of player a so
he's really suggesting you know exist
waste not just that a computer would
take the place of a person to try to
suggest that they are in fact human but
that it would try to pretend to be a
woman he's with a more literal reading
would suggest now as we know the
mathematician Turing himself also had to
pass in his case is a straight man in a
society that criminalized homosexuality
and upon the discovery that he was not
what he appeared to be he was forced to
undergo horrific medical experiments
treatments
let's say known as chemical castration
and ultimately the physical and
emotional pain was too great and he'd
committed suicide
the episode being a grotesque tribute to
a man whose recent contribution to
defeating Hitler's military was still a
state secret
Turing should be said was only recently
given a posthumous pardon but tens of
thousands of other British men Centrum's
under similar laws today have not won
notes I think a kind of sour ironic
correspondence between asking an AI to
pass the test in order to qualify as
intelligent who passes a human
intelligence returns only to hide his
own animal sexuality and to pass as a
straight man the demands of both Bluffs
are unnecessary and profoundly unfair
and as for all passing the performances
success or failure reveals more about
the audience than about the performer in
other in other place in some fictions
policing the imitation game is a matter
of life and death the part of Ridley
Scott's film version of grand regime of
Electric Sheep from Blade Runner the
philip k dick novel hinges on the
voight-komp empathy test which
differentiates humans from reference in
this narrative replicants are throttled
in two important ways first they expire
after just a few years and two they have
ostensibly a rather diminished capacity
for empathy Deckard the Harrison Ford
character must retire a group of rogue
replicants but first you must find them
and in this world Turing test thresholds
are weaponized lest replicants pass as
humans and trespass beyond their station
by the film's conclusion Deckard who
himself may or may not be a replicant
develops a certain empathy we might say
for the replicants own desire for quote
more life an arguably they - at least
the Roy batty Rutger Hauer kiss
character seems to have empathy for
Deckard's own dilemma his dilemma and
ours is that in order to enforce the gap
between the human and the eye i define
by empathy or lack thereof
Deckert must suppress the empathy that
supposedly makes him uniquely human by
forcing him to quash his own
identification with the replicants that
supposedly cannot have empathy in return
the principle of differentiation
requires its own violation in order to
maintain itself far better I think to
examine in terms of sort of thinking
about how the AI might perform in this
way to examine how identification and
identification the production of the
effect of empathy works from our side of
the conversation
this is Paro the baby's robot seal by
the way it's clearly much easier to make
a robot that a human believes to have
emotions and for which a human in turn
may have emotions positive or negative
than it is to make a robot that actually
has those emotions the human may feel
love or hate or comfort from the eye but
he or she is reading cues not detecting
feelings what seems like empathy is
really a one way projection mistaken for
recognition like the Turing test itself
and not based on any mutual solidarity
will the wish to define the very
existence of AI in relationship to its
ability to mimic how humans think that
humans think will this be looked back on
in some weird form of species perhaps it
may also that the legacy this also that
the this legacy the older models of AI
research sending sent this research
account disappointingly fruitless paths
hoping to recreate human minds from top
down as the basic structure and it just
doesn't work
Stuart Russell and Peter Norvig remind
us and they're essential AI textbook
biomorphic imitation is not generally
how we decide about complex technology
airplanes don't fly like birds and we
certainly don't try to convince try to
trick birds into thinking that airplanes
are birds in order to test whether these
planes really are flying machine
so why do we do this for AI today the
vast majority of real serious core AI
researchers not focus on the Turing test
is anything like a central criterion of
success other than H AI I are human
artificial touch interaction research as
the criterion of success yeah in a
general popular discourse about AI the
tests or versions of its insert the
anthropocentrism there uphold such still
such conceptual importance like the
animals who talk like teenagers in a
Disney movie other minds are conceivable
mostly by way of pure aisle
ventriloquism should a I arrive it will
not be human-like unless we insist that
it pretend to be so because one assumes
the idea that intelligence could be both
real and inhuman at the same time as
somehow morally or psychologically
intolerable instead of nurturing this
bigotry we move to better to allow that
in our universe thinking is a much more
diverse even alien phenomenon than our
own particular case thus the real
philosophical issues and lessons of AI
will have less to do with humans
teaching machines how to think than with
machines teaching humans a fuller and
truer range of what thinking is and can
be now in addition to the
demystification and expansion of
thinking in this way and the relocation
of human sapiens within this expanded
field the sensory media of synthetic
intelligence may also contribute to a
certain kind of undermining of certain
forms of a durable content sort of
distilled philosophical distinction
between thinking and sensing discussion
so I want to hone in a bit on the ways
in which that kind of cartographic
abstraction mapping what's out there can
in fact also be thermal related to skin
how it occupies it agitates skin's human
skins building skins any school and how
this does so officer for the purpose
mapping and so I touch briefly on these
extending what something like a skin
based media aperture sorry and epidermal
media can be almost keep with the skin
with humans photo we recognized that
wealth in the late 19th century cinema
and photography allowed for to be
possible to compose and to see sorts of
images we had never seen before
montage slow-motion double exposure and
so forth and the same goes the synthetic
and recorded sound or auditory senses
our largest sensory organ is our skin
and however quite obviously today we
have not developed nearly as diverse
forms of sophisticated forms of
artificial touch or tactility or feeling
for skin based media as we have for
vision and hearing clothing are you
least one way that we have leapfrog
genetic evolution to augment skin ie
faster faster than evolving fur or
blubber is to engineer scuba suits so
part of the research that working in one
practical research engaged with UC San
Diego with the Center for design geo
politics in collaboration with our
Department of nano engineering
bioengineering is some exploratory
research on how this or let's say the
presume space of difference between
natural selection on the one hand and
machine sensing on the other is alighted
by certain technologies that operate in
and on the skin and at the scale of our
dermal and epidermal somatosensory
system mechanoreceptors thermo receptors
and so forth and by this I don't mean
some kind of triple o word game by which
McLeish machines are bequeath with pan
psychic capacities for of intuition
effect rather I refer to real-deal
technologies by which biological and
non-biological physicochemical reactions
are literally interwoven in and at the
scale on the sense8 skin artificial
skins are also among one of the more
areas of design research more generally
in this way DARPA for example is long
funded research into advanced
prosthetics and currently one of the
research tracks
focuses on providing from a synthetic
tactile sensation
sort of virtual fingertips that might go
in the end of those prosthetics people
go actually wearing them to field use
them as a way to feel and to touch the
world and other kinds of dermal surfaces
of poor that would enable a corporeal
extensions for the wear and another as I
say in other labs near us when can find
varieties of epidermal micro electronics
that augment the living skins capacities
for sensing internal or extra internal
or external symmetry next order these
nanoscale chemistry cooks up inks that
react to the presence of ambient trace
elements of whatever particles they're
tuned to react with and so designing
chemical sensitivity a core near the
atomic level in this case and the
registration of those as a transmissible
information with dermal and epidermal
microelectronics at larger scales we can
conceive really of a real immediate
ization of sense8 surfaces together
these technologies suggest something
like a skin based micro stack comprised
of biological and chemical and
mechanical sensing and processing in
various combinations as an emergent
formulation of wearable computing here
also including biochemical reactions it
blends as I say animal sensation machine
sensing into a kind of composite
surficial media there's platforms for
haptic interfaces of touch and motion
interfaces it's terms of code
interaction may be below or above normal
perceptual scales and may involve
autonomic nervous reactions as much as
if not more than the relatively blunt
gestures of hands and thumbs today's and
these dermal epidermal media both the
ones we have the ones who are in the
ones that we anticipate make it possible
to sense things about the external world
other work that our skin otherwise is
not able to register particulate matter
sense of the scale of parts per trillion
or things about our internal state of pH
balance in your sweat whatever but the
longer-term and really more interesting
design horizon for skin based media are
ones that would allow bodies novel and
unnatural forms of type sensation
that we have perhaps never experienced
before pleasure and pain are on the menu
but more besides so think of it this way
again early in experimental media and
their innovations with within artificial
visions and sights and sounds is one
precedent but also perhaps is molecular
gastronomy in the rebuilding of food
from first principles on up and if we
include taste is a particularly nuanced
form of touch which of course it is then
what are today novel tastes are models
for new sensations to come the same
holds true
I would hope the argue for the redesign
of the surfaces of the city its skins
urban interfaces are also sensory
mechanisms sometimes they're binary
gateways that allow a prohibited mission
to through the domain other times there
are reactive skins that sense threshold
events by reacting to light sound or
touch ambient trace elements and as we
meander the city these interfaces are
also our habitats and we dwell within
them but they are dwelling as well
they sense us as their world and we are
their habitat as much as they are ours
we are organisms living inside of them
just as they are inside of us ubiquitous
computing at and in the city skins and
surfaces and interfaces we see as
something like urbanism as nested
parasitism or nested parasitism as
urbanism no from touching to see by
shifting this line of inquiry up to this
urban scale illustrate what we take to
be the artificially mediated service
includes things that are analogous to
skin but we're job but we but also those
things that we would today referred to
colloquially as a kind of machine vision
quote unquote now vision has evolved
independently many times in evolutionary
history and arguably in the past two
decades or so it has evolved again this
time not for cuttlefish or rattles
but for Network CCD sensors and
algorithmic armatures processing what is
sensed into differentiating
differentiating and motivated
recognition and cognition
quote unquote visual sensors responding
to light often but not always shaped
like cameras are one kind of design
surface capable of synthetic sensation
and computational interpretation but in
the wider urban landscape they to
co-mingle with networks of other
surficial sensors responding to motion
and pressure and heat and ambient air
quality so forth and so on and so again
to the extent that it's
epistemologically and functionally
convenient we call these variously
machine vision machine hearing machine
skin but of course any real
correspondence to and from the mammalian
sensory apparatus is nearly allegorical
the AI city may be embodying itself but
as I'll say a few times not as we do now
as for the media technologies that
length or to let link these together
inserting into a particular question of
vision or light since we we might say
that when information is scarce then
copying something is the work of the
mechanical image however when
information is abundant especially when
it's over abundant then seeing the
original picking its pattern out of the
background this is the work of machine
vision for thinking animals seeing and
making things is easy but making copies
of what isn't seen and made it hard for
machines on the other hand making copies
is a way of seeing that is much easier
than thinking or perhaps is a kind of
thinking and in the varied history of
the multiple and as I say independent
evolutionary careers of vision various
photoreceptor cells found across the
phylum a have evolved from many
different kinds of chemoreceptors and
most likely well in advance of anything
we might recognize as a fully fledged
brain like information processing organ
further we could say that photosynthesis
is also and there's a chemical response
to light and so in the broadest sense it
too could be considered as a kind of
vision without images no within the
animal Ian's vision image making Nexus
the one that we most successful is of
course primarily human and it's likely
that from the beginning to the end of
the Holocene that the total quantity of
images that humans have produced from
cave walls to face time measures
I don't know per year total pounds of
images total terabytes of information
supports continues to increase
exponentially now with digital imaging
machines in everyone's pocket the raw
sum of total images produced someone's
in Cincy or 2005 authors argue 2008 may
be more than all of those produced up to
that moment it depends of course on how
you define and quantify an image but the
vulture benjamin call the mechanical
reproducing roosters reproducibility has
certainly allowed images to proliferate
far beyond the means of human craft
further today many images are made for
no one but this does not mean that
they're functionalist they are made by
and for machines that see the world
differently than we do those machines
don't have eyeballs or rods and cones or
visual cortex but they do have sensors
that detect light in motion and form and
heat in color in other ways in such
today that the industrial scale
processing of that data that has been
gleaned by scanning the light spectrum
in some way from urban scale Street
surveillance can millimeter scale
quality control along assembly lines
represents a significant fraction of all
of the work that the world does to image
itself for the purpose of governing
human society the end of the day the
machining phylum may take more selfies
than cells do however the function of
representation at work here is probably
rather
the quote-unquote image may likely
remain data that has never rerender to
look like a picture because there's no
need an algorithm program to discern a
particular pattern or anomaly can see it
directly in the data itself it doesn't
necessarily need for that data to be
projected as if for a mammal and then
reaching and reinterpreted back into
code like any like like any algorithmic
scanning and sorting of a any large data
set the fact that the original source
was or is visual is not so critical so
again like plants do machines also
possess a kind of vision without images
or at least a kind of image a kind of
image with that suggests a very
different form of abstraction toward a
very different kind of corporeal
experience that is a an abstraction
that's based on chemical or
informational pattern finding as as that
cartographic simulation of experience or
as that experience itself perhaps
surprising to some perhaps not to others
then that the function of machine ik
images today and up there abstractions
both animal and algorithmic is in many
cases if not actually predominantly to
determine the veracity and originality
of what those images supposedly
represent for example some of the shapes
printed on dollar bills or euros or
Swiss francs of take your pick are there
for humans to differentiate the value of
one token from another but far more our
for machine vision counterfeit detection
to verify that this is a real dollar the
piece of paper is full of machines that
happen to look like pictures and it is
an image as machine or a surveillance
scan of a city may pick out one face one
body from the thousands of motions
looking for the one true target
elsewhere we insert tiny camera probes
into great paintings to verify that they
are originals this is often required by
insurance companies
purchases online capture software shows
us an image and then in a quick
inversion of the Turing test analyzes
how the human user interprets it to
determines if they are in fact a real
person so we conclude perhaps that venue
means assurances that mechanical
reproduction would undermine the aura of
the original is true when for example we
compare a painting with a postcard of a
painting
however machine vision and images as
machines are put to work to ensure our
attic originals verified non fakes true
identities unbroken versions normal
targets certified real deals and so a
kind of revolution is made back around
as the image is more fully technologized
as it becomes itself a machine in some
cases then menu means historical art
from the pre mechanical original to
mechanical copy is incomplete without
another curve leading now to what the
machine is authentic
still if we if we if cities are always
in there some way about vision to some
degree in again benjamine makes an
appearance here's what as well we think
of this in terms of how we see it which
is fun or see each other through it also
fine but should also think of it in
terms of how it sees on its own terms
the machine ik visual subject that it
puts forth is not something that's that
possesses necessarily human-like or
human level perceptual and aesthetic
capacities of discernment of connoisseur
ship but rather something that is
interesting because it does not possess
those things and yet can see us
recognize us and know us regardless and
that's weird enough so there's the
question on the Waggoner how the world
looks as a screen and another more
important I think is how we look as
objects of perception from the position
of machines with which we co-op I that
world
seeing ourselves through the eyes of
this machine and other who does not and
cannot have an effective sense of
aesthetics is a kind of disenchantment
we are just stuff in the world for
distributed and machine cognition to
look at and to make sense of our own
sapiens is real and unique but but as we
are things to observe that just happened
to be sapiens this doesn't really matter
to machine vision this decision
challenge I think is more than just like
hearing the sound of the record this
recorded sound of your voice on tape
that can't possibly be me it's
potentially the clearing away of a more
closely guarded illusion this
uncomfortable recognition in the
machines mirror is a kind of perhaps a
reverse uncanny valley that is instead
of being creeped out at how slightly
inhuman the creature in the image
appears were creeped out at how unhuman
we ourselves look through the creatures
eyes know the politics of this are also
that person is worse
frog mentally you're writing a book has
been doing about artificial intelligence
I found in some ways I didn't expect
that it's in many ways fully impossible
to separate the technology itself from
the sometimes bizarre ideas that we have
for it and about it and as I'm
fascinated by how technologies are not
only anthropomorphised
but how some are considered menacing and
others amazing and some both at once
there's a way in which part of this is a
part of a genealogy that we might take
you know at least through the Taos and
the influencing machine the ways in
which this this apparatus just beyond
our understanding come to take on a kind
of psychiatric significance whether the
aliens are reading your thoughts through
radio waves and dental implants or
Google is reading your thoughts through
the email the borderlands between
schizophrenia and sensible vigilance
delusion and deductions are disputed
territory
perhaps it comes down to a level of
discomfort not just
how some people see technologies but
with how some people think of
technologies see them the occult
artifacts of planetary scale computation
are a cracked mirror and reflections
seen there are given to a manichaean and
dualistic and sometimes even bipolar
political psychiatric imaginary for
example deep dream last summer was here
we have this the deep dreams that these
are do so to tell you about these in a
moment that is appropriate approvals
research had released sometimes the
summer be fo Franco Berardi and I were
having breakfast as well he and I we
don't particularly see we don't usually
think about Google in the same way so
let's say but we were both totally
amazed by these images with this as well
as other sort of ongoing conversations
about this really read these represent a
new kind of image we haven't seen the
board so in such a long time
so those of you want to familiar with
these as well basically what your second
then on that to have summer day last
june happen to be on the front page of
every newspaper was a project undertaken
by google research where notions a sort
of object and out sort of feature
recognition algorithms that will analyze
large datasets to look for particular
things how it is that your photo app
knows you know which would face you are
that's a horse or a dog with russia this
is well they're interested in a ways
like how do you what kind of feedback
loops could this sort of provide what
happens if it tries to see something
that's not there but you force it to see
it organ or you ask it to see it so
often this as well and this is kind of
what this done in this simplest sort of
explanation there's the process is kind
of simple find edges function like you
might do in photoshop where you sort of
filter the image just to make the edges
everything a bit more what it is in
relationship good things around it you
then ask me to look for the thing that
it's looking for and then you do this
again and then you've good again and
then again and you feed this back
through the system over and over and
over and over and over again and it
starts to actually compress the image
and start to find things that it's
looking for that aren't actually they're
a kind of AI hallucination if you like
now there's a bunch of websites you can
go to you can take your own vacation
photos and upload them and have them
dreama fine if you like food is horrible
to do this as well
porn also will not recommend it
no the images I think are remarkable
enough on their own irrespective of
their Providence but once the viewer I
think makes the partial of course it's
always partial empathetic transference
into the other mind of this feature
recognition algorithm and its way of
seeing something the effect in a way I'm
kind of trying on a new mode of
perception making sense of the work
through those eyes actually that's the
real payoff even if it's an example as I
say here of a kind of AI apophenia the
false positive as a court so what is the
front tuck stop on this for a moment
what is apathy apathy Nia is the it's a
psychological phenomenon of false
pattern recognition or you see a pattern
in something that's not really there
pareidolia is the subtype of fine
rabbity where you see faces and things
that aren't really there and receive
them whether you mean whether you want
to or not you can say it's not a face I
know it's not a face you're going to see
a face it's not necessarily a kind of
process that you can be you know the
disenchanted oh by just by being told so
away but it's a it's a you know
causation causality dynamic where you
see some correspondence between things
in it and you deduce that there must be
some causal relationship between these
two things in general if these sort of
pattern structures of apathy conspiracy
theory is a placenta as a form of
political science if you like in this
one as well but it's who we are and what
we do it's in this kind of pattern
finding even the false pattern finding
is intrinsic and necessary to our
evolution into our sapiens we are who we
are and can't sort of done without it
think of it this way there's a character
I'll tell you so there's character and
Peter Walter Eason almost one of a
handful of really good novels about AI
novel called echo Pratt CO and in this
story one of the character relays this
this this this
explaining apophenia to one of the other
characters in the in the novel the
character then argues that this false
pattern-recognition is hardwired into
our Homo sapiens evolutionary success
and the story goes like this tens of
thousands of years ago two guys are
hiding in the tall grass quietly looking
around for both predator and prey one of
them sees a faint but distinct anomaly
in the way the light breaks through the
grass moving left to right and he
recognizes this pattern as that of a
looming cat and runs away back to the
village leaving his friend who does not
possess those pattern recognition genes
to be eaten the guy who ran away was
able to reproduce his pattern
recognition genes ensure his and their
survival and the guy who did not possess
those genes did not reproduce simple as
that
however there was a third guy sitting in
a similar grass perhaps the morning
earlier he too thought there was a tiger
and got up and ran back to the safety of
the village but in this case there was
no Tiger it was all in his mind he was
not cunning he was paranoid yet he too
was able to respond reproduce and his
faulty pattern recognition genes which
are perhaps actually the same thing as
the first guy's accurate pattern
recognition genes were also able to
reproduce as well perhaps with the
second guys
wife I don't know the lesson is that
evolution has greatly rewarded both
positive human successful human pattern
recognition but is also bound
inextricably bound inextricably to the
bounty of that bargain
it has also rewarded hallucination and
error and so it's one thing to caution
paranoia about Google but it's but it's
not as if Google's algorithms are
themselves as if they are not themselves
also deeply paranoid after all they see
psychedelic logs faces in everything now
the reason the deep dream hallucinates
dogs is itself not spooky its object
recognition faculties were used trained
during an image
data set called imagenet which is based
on various breeds of dogs you can treat
dogs all with different you train your
reckon should identify that the poodle
and a Great Dane I like they're all
constituted dog it's that's easier than
the you know it's it's this is a
difficult accomplishment and so it will
therefore hallucinate dogs where there
are none and to identify people as dogs
if it's told to look at them hard enough
now this ladder may seem insulting but
maybe it shouldn't you call the Diogenes
proto cause Napolitan ISM is based after
all and the glorious dog like community
of us all and so deep dreams images are
artifacts of computers hallucinations of
phantom conclusions then perhaps the
conspiratorial figure cut by Eagle goo
evil Google stepfather is that same
paranoid vision turn inside out and back
on itself perhaps the Google the AI is
this paranoid in how it sees us as some
of us are in how we see it it's not
coincidental or surprising then that as
AI matures its own pattern recognition
faculties would reach the plateau and
accomplishment of creative a plenum from
Antonin Artaud to Seymour Cray there's
no common ways in which we have
perceived some kind of homology between
abnormal human psychology and various
machine behaviors and so is machine
vision paranoid is our popular
understanding of machine vision paranoid
what is Google up to are they watching
you and if so who or what are they see
is our understanding of Google's
paranoid machine vision itself paranoid
making the paranoid AI that much more
paranoid in response in a word yes
is this how artificial intelligence
should evolve in relation shoe ship to
and autonomously from human intelligence
well if the pattern recognition is
pattern recognition human pattern
recognition is any indicator based both
on productive and destructive apathy Nia
deception and delusion then yes and no
so
moving then back up in scale to the AI
machine sensing as a whole at the level
of the whole city
and in this redistribution of the
resettable again the AI city may be
embodying itself but not as we do the
commingling of diverse sensors of light
and air and sound in chemistry draws a
landscape of sensing and thinking little
species partially embodied discretely
one with another and partially come
embodied with one another as their
information inputs are aggregated
modeled and acted upon in various
pluralities Homo sapiens comes equipped
with an extraordinary array of sensory
faculties which is we discuss may be
augmented further by synthetic layers in
various ratios ranging from the sensors
and trackers and our phones that we
carry about like meals to more intimate
media of strengths of artificial images
and sight and sounds
situating ourselves in this expanded
field again we are both sensors and
sensed on the one hand we are primary
sapient actor in the drama supervising
an orchestra of sensing technologies
each individually capable of functional
processing and together of certain forms
of aggregate emergent intelligence such
as SARS for example our neurons on the
other were not only the subject of the
scenario we are also its subject matter
then wider urban landscape of synthetic
sensory systems is not only a platform
through which we extend and extrapolate
our capacities for abstraction
distributed cognition it's also capable
of other sorts of abstraction on its own
there's part of its intelligence it
looks at us and registers abstractions
about us and again that not just a are
in the city but nested AI Co embodied as
the city with very different sorts of
organisms to population to genome
kanesha to signal morphologies at work
and thus the work of abstract
for organism for design more generally
is not only to deploy abstract forms but
to set in motion mechanisms and programs
that are capable of their own feats of
abstraction and to calibrate how they
abstract us and one another a quarter in
short we should imagine an AI urbanism a
bit consumed in sort of like Vienna
college stroll into the field populated
by intermingling but neutrally oblivious
little life worlds or terms of de luces
parable of the kick the later weight
laying in wait for some threshold event
to come its way at which point its
triggers programmed response leaping out
into its own little void many of our
urban sensors and their limited forms of
AI work similarly and with similar
nobility more versatile synthetic
intelligence occupy more complex will
develop some are predators and prey some
are in motion summer flowering some
pollinating and as we stroll along them
we may be registered by them or we may
be ignored may be a primary cause of
concern we may be a passing interference
in an evolutionary dynamic in which we
are neither the protagonist nor target
and this is anyway as we might expect
actually not so surprising as we we know
ships from top down to bottom up AI
particularly robotics have been marked
by shift of emphasis from intelligence
as a formal at the syntax to one of a
specifically embodied relation to
specific worlds and models heuristic
knowledge of habitats is seen as
inseparable from how an AI manipulates
is situated problem space and so in
robotics through the pairing of
synthetic sensing and visual for example
with algorithmic reasoning allows for
simple artificial species to perform
intelligently because they have what
amounts to functionally an embodied
perceptual location in the world they
can think because they can see
now the implications of all of this for
our politics of geopolitics and all the
rest of us as I say are fraught and
tangled and profound and banal in
various measures extends from the
biochemistry of climates and ecosystems
to the rhetorical conventions of
citizenship and sovereignty
it's Messier is what we're talking about
not a kind of clean and pure AI and so
I'll conclude presentation with a few
admonitions toward a general
interdisciplinary design grateful for AI
and for what we might call the post and
throughout the scene it is at best a
paradoxical accomplishment to survive a
mass extinction event the modern human
species has the dubious distinction of
not only observing and measuring mass
extinction while it has happened but
also doing so with the understanding
that it is one preen of the preeminent
agents of that event it does so with the
ambivalent comfort that that one way or
another it too is unlikely to survive
the bloody edge of the Anthropocene
intact as so much departs what arrives
simultaneously with the collapse of
biodiversity we also see at least the
strong potential for an explosion of new
quote-unquote species taking form
through robotics and synthetic biology
and artificial intelligence we can't see
the latter as replacements for the
former and yet there they are recall for
example that the first Earthlings in
space were not humans and that a very
low percentage of all Earthlings in
space have been humans human biology is
needy and fragile it is poorly suited to
space travel largely because we have to
bring an entire ecosystem with us from
oxygen to radiation filters to the
microbial biome in our test
could help us digest food as currently
configured humans we cannot really
believe earth because we have to bring a
miniature earth with us when we go this
is not true in the same way for other
species which should provide
comparatively easy in space such as
metalloid robotics and perhaps also
Sunday some kinds of synthetic biology
and so perhaps like the small mammals
that took about that took over after the
cretaceous-paleogene extinction they're
just better suited to the very different
punctuated equilibrium to come they may
enjoy successes that we cannot leaving
us behind and stranded in place so what
comes then after an Anthropocene
extinction the only thing we can know
about the post and throughout the scene
is that it's an era in which humans
would no longer be at the dominant
geologic actor perhaps a new earthling
species may prove to be more fit better
than making the next evolutionary steps
than humans are and so for us to quote
survive we may have to become more like
them and much like what we are now in
the longer view humans role may be that
of an enabling intermediary between
early primates and as yet to emerge
phyla that blend organic and inorganic
flesh and thinking this is the point of
convergence between robust AI and the
deep ecologies of voluntary human
extinction but instead of disappearing
however we may survive by perforating
the boundaries between animal vegetable
and mineral as a design is that as our
design problem and design solution and
so what are the stages the depth of the
user has a certain kind of death of a
student for humanism and the eclipse of
a certain sort of resolute humanism it
does so because it brings with it also
the multiplication and proliferation of
other forms of non-human in human actual
human agents and subjects including
censors and algorithms and robots from
nanometric to landscape-scale any
combination of which with which we may
enter into a kind of relationship as a
composite subject the complexities and
contradictions of those sovereignties in
relationship to those composites are
nevertheless in with those quasi
intelligent sensei's actors as I say
work to dismember certain conventional
distinctions between subject and true
occupant and city and so and so forth
introduces a certain kind of
redistribution of a certain kind of
agnostic universal suffrage by which set
what kinds of matter can enter into that
position to take on that to that throne
claiming is strongly a different kind of
strong materials perspective in
territory and but we anticipate without
a doubt but as this as this works itself
out as that disenchantment unfolds that
we anticipate all manner of pushback
against this demystified and demonized
mathematics not only distaste for
certain forms of quantification and a
preference for romantic verse for
example but a bulwark on behalf of what
amounts to a pre Copernican and deeply
reactionary humanist exceptionalism even
a humanist fundamentalism I push back as
I say as frivolous perhaps as rationally
irrational there there are that is
certain affinities with certain
technologies however fictitious of
bizarre those affinities maybe that are
thought to embody the essence of a kind
of Croatian astre one of these is food
or had certain forms of technologies of
personal mastery such as the car I think
when the Google X was beginning to work
on the driver the driverless car project
they want up and visited the labs up
there with a student of mine who was not
working on that tonight we're meeting
with in my essence you guys must have
heard a lot of different kind of strange
strange ideas about what the driverless
car system is going to amount to and how
what to sort of push back from it
that this is well and they say well
funny you should ask
they pull off this piece of paper which
is the intention to file a potential
file pre-emptive legal notice or
something which as far as they could
tell is just a completely made-up
document is no such thing from a group
called Gun Owners of America which is an
advocacy group a bit to the right of the
net out they Hannah right and and you
remember that in the United States alone
roughly about thirty thousand people a
year are killed in car accidents but
twenty and eight thousand a year of
those are directly attributable to human
driver error
and so if driverless cars could kill
twenty seven thousand people a year or
less they would still be a you know from
purely consequentialist view of ethical
bit of advantage and so the idea that it
would be under certain point league
determined for purposes of you know we
presume that putting a human behind the
wheel is just too great of a risk it's
just an unethical to put everyone else
at risk in this sort of set in this in
this kind of way it makes it makes sense
and so what this legal thing was with
this dog were saying is like should it
become illegal for humans to drive a car
in this way that they will seek to have
automobiles reclassified as ammunition
and thereby covered by the Second
Amendment of the Constitution which
guarantees the right to bear arms in
this case a car
or but this way your life may be ended
by someone encased in a two-ton steel
box careening down the asphalt trying to
prove a point about his how technology
will never capture his natural humanity
now although this is not without real
risk we we anticipate that this
distribution of perception and Co
embodiment implied by sensei AI at the
urban scale would if we are attentive
and persistent shift and expand what we
take to be an ethics of shelter and of
encounter of negotiation and even
immunity and in this the modern era of
form of urban anime may pale in
comparison to the challengers of
predator prey camouflage dissimulation
relationships implied by the emergence
of various alien minds of urban scale
negotiating our way to a livable postin
throughout the scene necessitates
however i still argue a fidelity to
emergence not to emergency because
Copernican traumas that abolish the
false centrality and specialness of
human thought and species being are
priceless accomplishments the advent of
robust inhuman AI could provide for
similar disenchantment one that should
enable a more reality based
understanding of ourselves of our
situation and a fuller and more complex
and nuanced understanding of what
intelligence is what thinking is and is
not and from there we can hopefully make
our world with greater confidence that
our models are good approximations of
what's out there always a helpful thing
an additional harm and an additional
harm of the alternative to that is in
perpetuating a relationship to
technology that has brought us to the
precipice of a sixth great extinction
arguably and I would make the argument
if the Anthropocene itself is do less to
technology run amok then to the humanist
legacy that
understands the world as having been
given for our needs and created in our
image we still see this everywhere our
computing culture is deeply confused and
so and is so along these same lines we
vacillate between thinking technology as
a transparent extension of our desires
on the one hand and of thinking of it as
an unstoppable and linear historical
course on the other for the first agency
is magically ours alone and for the
second agencies all in the code that's
gross inflation of the former is merely
inverted back into the other and this is
why we can't have nice things
well-known did thought leader in the
world of design recently read shelves
and peel and remain nameless quote it's
time to invert invent a world where
machines are subservient to the needs
and wishes of humanity quote simply
breathtaking if you think so I invite
you to Google pig decapitating machine
and then let's talk about inventing
worlds in which machines are wholly
subservient to human wishes one wonders
whether it's only from a society that
one scape theological and legislative
comfort to chattel slavery that this
particular claim could be offered with
such satisfied naivete this is the
sentiment this philosophy of technology
exactly that is the basic algorithm of
answer the scenic predicament it's time
to move on this pretentious folklore is
too expensive and so but to put in goods
put differently please to make
technology serve humans and serve human
needs and desires requirements appear
utterly misguided and even suicidal
scaring upon the abyss of mass
extinction we hear the dreary early
common refrain variously explicit or
latent that identifies quote modern
technology as the main culprit and
conclusion that the most fundamental
solution is 2d technologies the planet
and to Rehim annoys ourselves one
presupposing the other in very
measures this is among the worst
possible plans both philosophically and
practically first it's tragically death
to the priceless Copernican trauma of
the anthropogenic precipice that our
status as the dominant geologic actor is
fleeting and so in order to survive you
have to become something that is not
necessarily recognizably human and
seconded props up a psychotic
misrepresentation about humans and
humanism actually are we or the
brain-eating Apes with weaponized
hydrogen atoms who organize their
societies according to Bronze Age poetry
on human sacrifice and ritual
purification among the last projects to
support is Rehan ization in any sense of
a direct return to historical norms I
think the other species would agree but
lastly the word of desire then how do we
mount this for technological material
recompensing as a theory of subjectivity
against the tropes or with the tropes of
heroes and sanitize its treatment
Freud barely had Darwin to work with let
alone genetics and genomics and so as
you probably read those terms you're
probably Brett we read a little bit like
one reads the Greeks organic vs.
inorganic that is whether something is
alive or not alive is kind of the miner
is sort of a minor issue or something
having our not having a carbon molecule
this is what the point something goes
organic is it this thing any any melting
back into the inorganic with an atomic
impulse no into the over comment
overwhelmed by an absorbed by matter
itself may be a way of encountering and
either desiring death perhaps but it's
also in many ways a very everyday kind
of occurrence it's not a sad destiny to
be interwoven in a matter and other
diagram and other diagrams for that
dissolution of possible both anatomic
and economic the human body and this
earthly landscape of matter are only the
default settings they're not destiny
chemistry may drive the most radical
forms of the philosophical imaginary to
come a culinary materialism is what puts
it yes
rubbing the Clinton raw and so here
among the algorithms that whining
evolution revision returns to the
primordial function of scanning the
landscapes for food friend and foe and
learning to think in relationship to
that mammoth some alternatives some of
them actually do this in a way I think
make the inevitable whether we wanted to
a not geoengineering project that really
actually constitutes the eco geopolitics
for at least the 20th century to
something that is either just a
disqualified a priori as a metaphysical
atrocity or something that will simply
sort itself automatically by the
invisible hand of Moore's law the former
is animated in various guises by a kind
of mystical primitive primitive ISM that
is to me the Theologica of a mode of
global dwelling that sees the world this
year for us based on a fetishization of
human experience of human experience
that takes priority over the materiality
of the emergent intelligence again it is
this humanist exceptionalism that is the
exact recipe for a patina product
predicament and the accomplishment of a
viable post answers renfa-sama
necessitates its refusal in this
fetishization of the experience of
experience as as an authentic
inferiority for one or the psychotic
proposition that somehow the self is a
stable physical entity that can be
expanded exponentially by the various
forms of computation without exploding
into some fractal plurality as for the
singularity people both of these make
that geoengineering project much more
and what does make it harder to
recognize it for what it should be
something that is more like molecular
gastronomy at landscape scale a resort
and recent and restored ecology designed
to taste itself in new forms of richly
spiced and imaginatively sauced mutual
ingestion last word less I misunderstood
to recommend too much of today's
computational culture this model for the
AI design that I'm sketching I'll end by
misquoting a sentence from Adorno's
minima moralia substituting the word
smart cities for his original topic of
escapist cinema it is not because they
turn their back on washed-out existence
that smart cities are so repugnant but
because they do not do so energetically
enough because they are themselves just
as washed out because the satisfactions
they fake coincide with the ignominious
have no dream